<bill session="116" type="s" number="2215" updated="2020-10-29T04:41:05Z">
  <state datetime="2019-07-23">REFERRED</state>
  <status>
    <introduced datetime="2019-07-23"/>
  </status>
  <introduced datetime="2019-07-23"/>
  <titles>
    <title type="official" as="introduced">A bill to prohibit agreements between employers that directly restrict the current or future employment of any employee.</title>
    <title type="short" as="introduced">End Employer Collusion Act</title>
    <title type="short" as="introduced">End Employer Collusion Act</title>
    <title type="display">End Employer Collusion Act</title>
  </titles>
  <sponsor bioguide_id="B001288"/>
  <cosponsors>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="W000817" joined="2019-07-23"/>
  </cosponsors>
  <actions>
    <action datetime="2019-07-23">
      <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2019-07-23" state="REFERRED">
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions.</text>
    </action>
  </actions>
  <committees>
    <committee subcommittee="" code="SSHR" name="Senate Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions" activity="Referral"/>
  </committees>
  <relatedbills>
    <bill type="h" session="116" relation="unknown" number="3920"/>
  </relatedbills>
  <subjects>
    <term name="Labor and employment"/>
    <term name="Civil actions and liability"/>
    <term name="Competition and antitrust"/>
    <term name="Contracts and agency"/>
    <term name="Employee hiring"/>
    <term name="Employment discrimination and employee rights"/>
    <term name="Labor-management relations"/>
  </subjects>
  <amendments/>
  <summary date="2019-07-23T04:00:00Z" status="Introduced in Senate">End Employer Collusion Act

This bill makes it unlawful for any entity to enter into a restrictive employment agreement, or to enforce or threaten to enforce a restrictive employment agreement. A "restrictive employment agreement" is any agreement between two or more employers that prohibits or restricts one employer from soliciting or hiring another employer's employees or former employees.

Any employer that has in effect a franchise agreement that includes a restrictive employment agreement that was entered into before enactment of this bill must amend the franchise agreement to remove such agreement.

The bill allows aggrieved individuals to bring a civil action for actual and punitive damages, plus attorney's fees, against an entity that enters into, or threatens to enforce, or fails to remove, a restrictive employment agreement.

The bill grants the Federal Trade Commission the power to enforce the requirements of this bill.</summary>
  <committee-reports/>
</bill>
