<bill session="116" type="h" number="4625" updated="2020-12-03T13:23:02Z">
  <state datetime="2019-11-12T16:26:18-05:00">PASS_OVER:HOUSE</state>
  <status>
    <unknown datetime="2019-11-12T16:26:18-05:00"/>
  </status>
  <introduced datetime="2019-10-08"/>
  <titles>
    <title type="short" as="introduced">Protect the GI Bill Act</title>
    <title type="short" as="introduced">Protect the GI Bill Act</title>
    <title type="short" as="passed house">Protect the GI Bill Act</title>
    <title type="short" as="passed house">Protect the GI Bill Act</title>
    <title type="official" as="introduced">To amend title 38, United States Code, to require that educational institutions abide by certain principles as a condition of approval for purposes of the educational assistance programs of the Department of Veterans Affairs, and for other purposes.</title>
    <title type="display">Protect the GI Bill Act</title>
  </titles>
  <sponsor bioguide_id="L000593"/>
  <cosponsors>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="C001068" joined="2019-11-12"/>
  </cosponsors>
  <actions>
    <action datetime="2019-10-08">
      <text>Introduced in House</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2019-10-08" state="REFERRED">
      <text>Referred to the House Committee on Veterans' Affairs.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2019-10-14">
      <text>Referred to the Subcommittee on Economic Opportunity.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2019-10-16">
      <text>Subcommittee on Economic Opportunity Discharged.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2019-10-16">
      <text>Committee Consideration and Mark-up Session Held.</text>
    </action>
    <calendar datetime="2019-10-16" state="REPORTED">
      <text>Ordered to be Reported (Amended) by Voice Vote.</text>
    </calendar>
    <action datetime="2019-11-12T16:06:20-05:00">
      <text>Mr. Takano moved to suspend the rules and pass the bill, as amended.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2019-11-12T16:06:33-05:00">
      <text>Considered under suspension of the rules.</text>
      <reference ref="CR H8746-8751" label="consideration"/>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2019-11-12T16:06:34-05:00">
      <text>DEBATE - The House proceeded with forty minutes of debate on H.R. 4625.</text>
    </action>
    <vote how="by voice vote" type="vote" datetime="2019-11-12T16:26:18-05:00" where="h" result="pass" state="PASS_OVER:HOUSE">
      <text>On motion to suspend the rules and pass the bill, as amended Agreed to by voice vote.</text>
      <reference ref="CR H8746-8749" label="text"/>
    </vote>
    <action datetime="2019-11-12T16:26:21-05:00">
      <text>Motion to reconsider laid on the table Agreed to without objection.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2019-11-13">
      <text>Received in the Senate and Read twice and referred to the Committee on Veterans' Affairs.</text>
    </action>
  </actions>
  <committees>
    <committee subcommittee="" code="SSVA" name="Senate Veterans' Affairs" activity="Referral"/>
    <committee subcommittee="" code="HSVR" name="House Veterans' Affairs" activity="Markup, Referral"/>
    <committee subcommittee="Economic Opportunity" code="HSVR10" name="House Veterans' Affairs" activity="Discharged, Referral"/>
  </committees>
  <relatedbills>
    <bill type="h" session="116" relation="unknown" number="4654"/>
    <bill type="h" session="116" relation="unknown" number="4312"/>
  </relatedbills>
  <subjects>
    <term name="Armed forces and national security"/>
    <term name="Congressional oversight"/>
    <term name="Government information and archives"/>
    <term name="Government lending and loan guarantees"/>
    <term name="Marketing and advertising"/>
    <term name="Military personnel and dependents"/>
    <term name="State and local government operations"/>
    <term name="Student aid and college costs"/>
    <term name="Veterans' education, employment, rehabilitation"/>
  </subjects>
  <amendments/>
  <summary date="2019-10-08T04:00:00Z" status="Introduced in House">Protect the GI Bill Act

This bill imposes requirements and restrictions on educational institutions participating in the educational assistance programs of the Department of Veterans Affairs (VA).

The bill limits participation in VA educational assistance programs if an educational institution (1) does not perform specified actions, such as providing cost information to individuals prior to enrollment; (2) implements fraudulent recruiting techniques or pays inducements to secure enrollments; or (3) is the subject of a negative action by its accrediting agency. The state approving agency or the VA shall impose limitations by publishing a warning or temporarily prohibiting the pursuit of a course of education at an institution.

The bill provides for waivers of certain requirements for a one-year period, but waivers may not be provided for more than two consecutive academic years.

The bill also prohibits the VA from approving the enrollment of an eligible veteran or eligible person in any course offered by an institution engaged in substantial misrepresentation (e.g., misrepresenting the size, location, facilities, or equipment of the institution).

Finally, the bill modifies the criteria that non-accredited courses must meet to be eligible for educational assistance. The bill adds requirements for (1) the educational institution offering the course to refrain from substantial misrepresentation; and (2) the state approving agency to review advertising, sales, or enrollment materials used by the institution.</summary>
  <committee-reports/>
</bill>
