<bill session="116" type="h" number="2486" updated="2020-12-28T14:41:01Z">
  <state datetime="2019-12-05">PASS_BACK:SENATE</state>
  <status>
    <unknown datetime="2019-12-05"/>
  </status>
  <introduced datetime="2019-05-02"/>
  <titles>
    <title type="short" as="introduced">Fostering Undergraduate Talent by Unlocking Resources for Education Act</title>
    <title type="short" as="introduced">FUTURE Act</title>
    <title type="short" as="passed house">Fostering Undergraduate Talent by Unlocking Resources for Education Act</title>
    <title type="short" as="passed house">FUTURE Act</title>
    <title type="short" as="passed senate">Fostering Undergraduate Talent by Unlocking Resources for Education Act</title>
    <title type="short" as="passed senate">FUTURE Act</title>
    <title type="short">Access to Counsel Act of 2020</title>
    <title type="short">Affordable Prescriptions for Patients Act of 2020</title>
    <title type="short">National Origin-Based Antidiscrimination for Nonimmigrants Act</title>
    <title type="short">NO BAN Act</title>
    <title type="official" as="introduced">To reauthorize mandatory funding programs for historically Black colleges and universities and other minority-serving institutions.</title>
    <title type="display">FUTURE Act</title>
  </titles>
  <sponsor bioguide_id="A000370"/>
  <cosponsors>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="B001305" joined="2019-09-16"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="C001097" joined="2019-09-17"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="C001123" joined="2019-09-16"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="C001068" joined="2019-09-11"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="C001053" joined="2019-07-16"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="C000754" joined="2019-09-11"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="D000617" joined="2019-09-11"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="F000466" joined="2019-08-23"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="F000449" joined="2019-09-10"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="G000552" joined="2019-08-16"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="G000551" joined="2019-09-17"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="H001080" joined="2019-09-17"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="H001090" joined="2019-09-11"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="H001083" joined="2019-09-16"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="J000288" joined="2019-09-17"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="K000392" joined="2019-09-16"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="L000570" joined="2019-09-10"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="N000147" joined="2019-09-16"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="O000171" joined="2019-08-16"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="P000258" joined="2019-08-23"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="P000523" joined="2019-09-16"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="R000575" joined="2019-09-10"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="R000613" joined="2019-09-17"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="S001177" joined="2019-09-10"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="S001205" joined="2019-09-11"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="T000193" joined="2019-09-11"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="T000484" joined="2019-07-16"/>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="W000819" joined="2019-05-02"/>
  </cosponsors>
  <actions>
    <action datetime="2019-05-02">
      <text>Introduced in House</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2019-05-02" state="REFERRED">
      <text>Referred to the House Committee on Education and Labor.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2019-09-17T17:15:13-04:00">
      <text>Ms. Adams moved to suspend the rules and pass the bill, as amended.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2019-09-17T17:15:25-04:00">
      <text>Considered under suspension of the rules.</text>
      <reference ref="CR H7734-7737" label="consideration"/>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2019-09-17T17:15:27-04:00">
      <text>DEBATE - The House proceeded with forty minutes of debate on H.R. 2486.</text>
    </action>
    <vote how="by voice vote" type="vote" datetime="2019-09-17T17:37:21-04:00" where="h" result="pass" state="PASS_OVER:HOUSE">
      <text>On motion to suspend the rules and pass the bill, as amended Agreed to by voice vote.</text>
      <reference ref="CR H7734-7735" label="text"/>
    </vote>
    <action datetime="2019-09-17T17:37:23-04:00">
      <text>Motion to reconsider laid on the table Agreed to without objection.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2019-09-18">
      <text>Received in the Senate.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2019-09-19">
      <text>Read the first time. Placed on Senate Legislative Calendar under Read the First Time.</text>
    </action>
    <calendar datetime="2019-09-23" calendar="Senate Legislative" under="General Orders" number="212">
      <text>Read the second time. Placed on Senate Legislative Calendar under General Orders. Calendar No. 212.</text>
    </calendar>
    <action datetime="2019-12-05">
      <text>Measure laid before Senate by unanimous consent.</text>
      <reference ref="CR S6865" label="consideration"/>
    </action>
    <vote how="by Voice Vote" type="vote2" datetime="2019-12-05" where="s" result="pass" state="PASS_BACK:SENATE">
      <text>Passed Senate with an amendment by Voice Vote.</text>
    </vote>
    <action datetime="2019-12-09">
      <text>Message on Senate action sent to the House.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2020-03-10T19:39:24-04:00">
      <text>Rules Committee Resolution H. Res. 891 Reported to House. Rule provides for consideration of S.J. Res. 68, H.R. 2486 and H.R. 6172. Resolution provides for consideration of S.J. Res. 68, the Senate amendment to H.R. 2486, and H.R. 6172. For S.J. Res. 68, the resolution provides for 1 hour of debate and 1 motion to commit. For the Senate amendment to H.R. 2486, the question will be divided and each portion will have 1 hour of debate. H.R. 6172 will have 1 hour ofdebate and 1 motion to recommit with or without instructions.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2020-07-22T10:29:30-04:00">
      <text>Pursuant to H. Res. 891, Ms. Jayapal was recognized to move that the House concur in the Senate amendment to H.R. 2486 with amendments specified in section 4 of H. Res. 891.</text>
      <reference ref="CR H3625-3638, H3666" label="consideration"/>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2020-07-22T10:30:47-04:00">
      <text>DEBATE - Pursuant H. Res. 891, the question shall be divided among the two House amendments. Pursuant to section 3(a) of H. Res. 891, the portion of the divided question comprising of the amendment specified in section 4(a) of H. Res. 891 shall be considered first. Each amendment specified in section 4 shall be debatable for one hour.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2020-07-22T10:37:04-04:00">
      <text>DEBATE - The House resumed debate on the House amendment to the Senate amendment.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2020-07-22T11:46:00-04:00">
      <text>The previous question was ordered pursuant to the rule.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2020-07-22T11:46:30-04:00">
      <text>POSTPONED PROCEEDINGS - At the conclusion of debate on the Jayapal motion that the House concur in the Senate amendment with an amendment specified in section 4(a) of H. Res. 891, the Chair put the question on adoption of the motion and by voice vote, announced that the ayes had prevailed. Mr. Nadler demanded the yeas and nays and the Chair postponed further proceedings on the motion until a time to be announced.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2020-07-22T11:47:00-04:00">
      <text>Pursuant to H. Res. 891, the House proceeded with one hour of debate on the motion that the House concur in the Senate amendment with an amendment specified in section 4(b).</text>
      <reference ref="CR H3638-3642, H3666-3667" label="consideration"/>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2020-07-22T12:12:20-04:00">
      <text>The previous question was ordered pursuant to the rule.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2020-07-22T12:12:42-04:00">
      <text>POSTPONED PROCEEDINGS - 1At the conclusion of debate on the Jayapal motion that the House concur in the Senate amendment with an amendment specified in section 4(b) of H. Res. 891, the Chair put the question on adoption of the motion and by voice vote, announced that the ayes had prevailed. Mr. Nadler demanded the yeas and nays and the Chair postponed further proceedings on the motion until a time to be announced.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2020-07-22T16:12:27-04:00">
      <text>On motion to concur in the Senate amendment with amendment specified in section 4(a) of H. Res. 891 Agreed to by the Yeas and Nays: 233 - 183 (Roll no. 153).</text>
      <reference ref="CR H3625-3628" label="text"/>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2020-07-22T16:51:32-04:00">
      <text>On motion to concur in the Senate amendment with amendment specified in section 4(b) of H. Res. 891 Agreed to by the Yeas and Nays: 231 - 184 (Roll no. 154).</text>
      <reference ref="CR H3638-3639" label="text"/>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2020-07-22T16:51:54-04:00">
      <text>Motion to reconsider laid on the table Agreed to without objection.</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2020-07-23">
      <text>Message on House action received in Senate and at desk: House amendments to Senate amendment.</text>
    </action>
  </actions>
  <committees>
    <committee subcommittee="" code="HSED" name="House Education and Labor" activity="Referral"/>
  </committees>
  <relatedbills>
    <bill type="h" session="116" relation="unknown" number="5363"/>
    <bill type="s" session="116" relation="identical" number="1279"/>
    <bill type="s" session="116" relation="unknown" number="1346"/>
    <bill type="hr" session="116" relation="unknown" number="891"/>
    <bill type="h" session="116" relation="unknown" number="4674"/>
    <bill type="h" session="116" relation="unknown" number="2214"/>
    <bill type="h" session="116" relation="unknown" number="3991"/>
    <bill type="h" session="116" relation="unknown" number="4398"/>
    <bill type="h" session="116" relation="unknown" number="5133"/>
    <bill type="h" session="116" relation="unknown" number="5581"/>
    <bill type="h" session="116" relation="unknown" number="640"/>
  </relatedbills>
  <subjects>
    <term name="Education"/>
    <term name="Area studies and international education"/>
    <term name="Education programs funding"/>
    <term name="Foreign language and bilingual programs"/>
    <term name="Higher education"/>
    <term name="Medical education"/>
    <term name="Minority education"/>
    <term name="Science and engineering education"/>
    <term name="Teaching, teachers, curricula"/>
    <term name="User charges and fees"/>
  </subjects>
  <amendments>
    <amendment number="s1255"/>
  </amendments>
  <summary date="2019-12-05T17:13:42Z" status="Passed Senate">Fostering Undergraduate Talent by Unlocking Resources for Education Act or the FUTURE Act

This bill requires the Internal Revenue Service (IRS) to disclose certain tax return information to the Department of Education (ED) for the purpose of administering financial aid and loan programs.

Upon receiving a request from ED, the IRS must disclose specified tax return information to ED for the purposes of

 establishing enrollment, renewing enrollment, administering, and conducting analyses and forecasts for estimating costs related to income-contingent or income-based repayment programs; discharging loans based on a total and permanent disability; determining the eligibility for, and the amount of, federal student financial aid; and conducting analyses and forecasts for estimating costs related to federal student financial aid programs. ED may only use the disclosed information for the purposes above and for mitigating risks related to the programs. Mitigation of&#160;risks includes conducting oversight and reducing improper payments. It does not include conducting criminal investigations or prosecutions.

With the consent of the taxpayer, ED may disclose the return information to certain institutions of higher education, state higher education agencies, and scholarship organizations solely for the use in financial aid programs.

The bill specifies notification and reporting requirements related to the disclosures and the implementation of the bill.

The bill also permanently extends funding for minority-serving institutions of higher education and increases funding for Pell Grants.</summary>
  <committee-reports/>
</bill>
