<bill session="116" type="s" number="4200" updated="2020-12-28T14:41:27Z">
  <state datetime="2020-07-22">REPORTED</state>
  <status>
    <unknown datetime="2020-07-22"/>
  </status>
  <introduced datetime="2020-07-02"/>
  <titles>
    <title type="short" as="introduced">Information Technology Modernization Centers of Excellence Program Act</title>
    <title type="short" as="reported to senate">Information Technology Modernization Centers of Excellence Program Act</title>
    <title type="display">Information Technology Modernization Centers of Excellence Program Act</title>
    <title type="official" as="introduced">A bill to establish a program to facilitate the adoption of modern technology by executive agencies, and for other purposes.</title>
  </titles>
  <sponsor bioguide_id="P000449"/>
  <cosponsors>
    <cosponsor bioguide_id="H001076" joined="2020-07-02"/>
  </cosponsors>
  <actions>
    <action datetime="2020-07-02">
      <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
    </action>
    <action datetime="2020-07-02" state="REFERRED">
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
    </action>
    <calendar datetime="2020-07-22" state="REPORTED">
      <text>Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs. Ordered to be reported with an amendment in the nature of a substitute favorably.</text>
    </calendar>
    <action datetime="2020-10-01">
      <text>Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs. Reported by Senator Johnson with an amendment in the nature of a substitute. With written report No. 116-277.</text>
    </action>
    <calendar datetime="2020-10-01" calendar="Senate Legislative" under="General Orders" number="570">
      <text>Placed on Senate Legislative Calendar under General Orders. Calendar No. 570.</text>
    </calendar>
  </actions>
  <committees>
    <committee subcommittee="" code="SSGA" name="Senate Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs" activity="Reporting, Markup, Referral"/>
  </committees>
  <relatedbills>
    <bill type="h" session="116" relation="unknown" number="5901"/>
  </relatedbills>
  <subjects>
    <term name="Government operations and politics"/>
    <term name="Computer security and identity theft"/>
    <term name="Computers and information technology"/>
    <term name="Executive agency funding and structure"/>
    <term name="General Services Administration"/>
    <term name="Infrastructure development"/>
    <term name="Public-private cooperation"/>
  </subjects>
  <amendments/>
  <summary date="2020-07-02T04:00:00Z" status="Introduced in Senate">Information Technology Modernization Centers of Excellence Program Act

This bill requires the General Service Administration (GSA) to establish an Information Technology Modernization Centers of Excellence Program to facilitate the adoption of modern technology by executive agencies.

The bill lists program responsibilities, including to

 modernize information technology used by an executive agency and how a customer interacts with the agency; improve cooperation between commercial and executive agency information technology sectors; encourage the adoption of commercial items; and assist executive agencies, on a reimbursable basis, with planning and adoption of technology in focus areas designated by the GSA, which may include, among other things, artificial intelligence. The GSA, for each reimbursable agreement entered into, shall make specified information available on a public website within 30 days of the signing of the agreement and updated upon completion.

This bill shall sunset seven years after its enactment.</summary>
  <committee-reports>
    <report>S. Rept. 116-277</report>
  </committee-reports>
</bill>
